Bas Machielsen

Email: a.h.machielsen@uu.nl

URL: http://bas-m.netlify.app

Github: https://github.com/basm92

Phone: (+31) 6 23 78 66 29

Born: September 30, 1992

Nationality: Dutch

Current positions

PhD Student, Utrecht University, Netherlands

I am a PhD student in economic history. My PhD research focuses on Dutch political elites and their economic interests, investment behavior, and political decision-making. My research is conducted within the framework of the NWO-project Investment behaviour, political change and economic growth in the Netherlands, 1780-1920. I am supervised by prof. dr. O. C. Gelderblom (Utrecht) and prof. dr. A. de Jong (Monash, EUR).

Academic Education

2017-2021	Linbergen Institute, 10 Economics PhD Courses
2018	Research Design Course, European University Institute, Florence, Italy
2015-2016	MSc in Economics, <i>cum laude</i> , Radboud University Nijmegen
2014-2015	MSc in Business Administration, University of Twente
2014-2015	Pre-MSc in Economics, Radboud University Nijmegen
2010-2013	BSc in Business Administration, University of Twente

Previous appointments

2020-2021	Teacher, Rotterdam School of Management, Erasmus University, Netherlands
2016-2017	Researcher, University of Twente, Enschede, Netherlands
2014-2015	Teaching Assistant to prof. dr. R.M. Kabir for Corporate Finance, Corporate Governance, Fi-
	nancial Accounting, University of Twente, Enschede, Netherlands

Other Education

2016-2020	Various completed courses on Coursera and other MOOC platforms, including Game Theory, Causal Inference, Bayesian Statistics, and 18 others.
2019	Posthumus Institute, Basic Training as part of PhD-programme
2018	Fundamentals of Statistics, Probability: The Science of Uncertainty and Data, MIT (EdX)

Presentations

2021	"Political Rents Under A Changing Electoral System", Economic History Association, Poster Ses-
	sion, Tucson, US (Canceled)
202I	"Democratization, Personal Wealth and Voting Behavior of Politicians", Economic History Sem-
	inar, Paris School of Economics, Paris, France
2020	N.W. Posthumus Economic History Graduate Conference, Erasmus University Rotterdam, Nether-
	lands
2020	"The Political Elite and the Welfare State", Graduate Seminar, Utrecht University, Utrecht, Nether-
	lands
2019	"The Wealth of the Political Elite in the Netherlands, 1877-1927", Financial History Seminar, Utrecht,
	Netherlands
2018	"The Influence of Electoral Constraints on the Composition of Politicians", Research Design
	Course for PhD students, Florence, Italy
2018	N.W. Posthumus Institute, PhD Seminar 2, Antwerp, Belgium
2017	N.W. Posthumus Institute, PhD Seminar 1, Brussels, Belgium
2016	"The drivers of profitability of Dutch Hospitals", University of Twente, Netherlands
	Teaching
2020-2021	BSc and MSc Theses Supervision, Rotterdam School of Management, Erasmus University
	Supervision of 10 groups of BSc students and 10 MSc students in various areas of finance.
	supervision of to groups of Doe students and to wise students in various areas of infance.
2018-2020	Big Data, Big Questions, undergraduate level, Utrecht University
	An undergraduate course about methodology and an introduction to data analysis.
2017-2019	Finance Bootcamp, Summer school Curious U, University of Twente, Netherlands
	A summer school on the basic principles of corporate finance and business valuation.
2014-2015	Teaching Assistant, Corporate Governance and Corporate Finance, University of Twente, Nether-

Programming Languages & Skills

R, Python, Stata, LATEX, git, bash, SQL, SAS, QGIS, Eviews, SPSS, HTML, CSS

Languages

lands

Dutch (native), English (full working proficiency), French (full working proficiency), Russian (full working proficiency), German (limited working proficiency), Turkish (elementary)

Miscellaneous & other activities

Creator, maintainer of several R packages, Member of PhD Council, PhD Representative N.W. Posthumus Institute, in possession of a driving licence.

Last updated: November 11, 2021